[Music]
Welcome to this Business Central launch
edition for the 2025 release wave 2. In
this session, we're going to talk about
what's new in server and database. My
name is Kenny Pontop and I'm the program
manager for this area. And with me, I
have Yens.
>> Yes. And I'm the engineering manager for
the server team in Business Central.
>> Yeah. And uh for all of these sessions
we do here at uh at the launch edition
we start talking I always start to talk
about the business value. So Yens what
is the business value of having a
server? Um well I guess it helps being
able to run some of the business logic
the partners have written in a
performant matter and um I guess that's
the main value proposition. It's
actually the engine running all of the
product.
>> It's a great answer.
>> So, thank you. Didn't quite expect that
question. Let's go.
>> Yes. So, we have a number of different
classes of things we want to talk about.
Uh AL runtime database reporting
tooling. So, let's dive in with new AL
methods. Uh we have three create sequ
sequential GUID lock timeout duration
and truncate. So the first uh is about
uh actually all the way back to when we
introduced system fields, system ID and
so on. We wanted to have an identifier
of all on all rows but in something that
would also be performant when you index
over it. So that's why a GUID is great
but GUID is horrible for indexing. So
that's why we stole the code from SQL
server to be able to do sequential
gooids and now we have also introduced
that logic in ale. So you can get kind
of a sequential gooid in case you want
to do the same.
>> Yes, usually if you have a good field
yourself for instance for logging
purposes etc. this actually helps
because it'll automatically put the log
entries together if particularly if it's
the primary key.
>> Yeah.
Um, we also have a new way to deal with
lock timeouts. So, the traditional lock
timeout method just have on and off,
true or false. Now, we have a way to set
a custom time time custom lock timeout
with a lock timeout duration method.
>> Yeah. And the cases where you want to do
use this is usually when you want
something that is not part of the UI
that is more resilient towards it taking
a little while to get a lock but you
don't want this almost infinite lock.
Now of course it's never infinite
because there's a command timeout as
well but that comes a lot later. So now
if you have something where you need a
bit more stability you can set it to for
instance 3 minutes or something like
that.
>> Yep.
And then uh we introduced a way to
delete I would say large amounts of
data. Uh so this is a new rec truncate
method. Truncate is a SQL method that is
much faster than delete. It's not
instantaneous. It is actually
transactional. And under this under the
hood the the difference between trunk
truncate and delete is truncate will
just lock in the transa transaction log
the page ids and not the full row. So
that's why it's faster. You can use it
for things like when you want to get rid
of uh like uh data for upgrade or batch
or uh staging tables things like that.
Uh the way we do it is we temporarily uh
drop sift indexes or views I said views
and then indexes uh while truncated and
then enabling them back. You can filter
so you don't have to truncate
everything. We'll then copy a portion to
a temporary table in SQL and then copy
it back once we have truncated. And you
can even keep your values on uh auto
increment. And that's kind of uh
everything there is to it.
>> Yeah. There's a few things to note here.
So you saw that we were copying data
out. So if you're not deleting the vast
majority of the table, don't use
truncate because it's counterproductive
because now you're moving a lot of data
in and out instead. And there are also
cases where truncate will return false.
So do remember to put it into an if
because here are here are actually the
full list if it is not a SQL table or
the table is a system table. Well, you
shouldn't have written truncate in that
case if it's inside a try function. But
there are also if security filters are
active because we can't truncate with
security filters because truncate takes
everything and with security filters
you're only allowed to see parts of the
data hence also delete parts of it. We
also have a limitation with media fields
because that requires us to maintain
media as well. And also if there are too
many rows that are marked or there are
filters on flow fields and last but not
least actually it's the one exactly in
the middle. If there are subscribers to
before or after delete we won't do the
truncate. So it's mainly used for log
logs etc as you said. And the way you
want to code this is you want to do an
if not rect truncate then maybe delete
all or whatever you want to do.
>> Yeah.
>> And I mean the on before on after delete
is simply because those things happen in
the AL runtime and truncate is a truly
databasecentric operation.
>> Yes. And we're not doing something rowby
row that's why it's a lot faster.
>> Yeah.
So that was actually leads us into
database features. Uh do you want to
take the first optimized flow field
calculations?
>> So this is an example of some of the
things we're working on under the hood
to make the service faster. Now for a
number of tables, they actually do sums
over other tables. For instance, GL
account, it has four flow fields on GL
entry. They are listed there. And when
we read those when doing autocal fields
we would actually do an outer apply for
each. Now we've improved the logic so
that they can use just one outer apply
and then it's just the actual um sum
statement that is different for these
which gives a significant performance
improvements if you're showing a lot of
calculated fields in a list page.
>> Yep. Another thing we did is you see it
in the data analysis or when you take
something in into analysis mode um in
three ways either on a query or if
server side analysis mode is when you
have more than 100,000 rows or if you uh
join to a related table. So these in
these three situations
the platform will go from browser side
where we load everything in the browser
into server side where we do it uh on
the server. So for that particular
server side analysis mode we can now
support the pivot operation on date
hierarchy fields. Whenever you have a
date, we do the year, quarter, month.
One more, I forgot. And then those um
can now be pivoted and they could you
couldn't do that before.
>> And actually the analysis mode has
become one of our most popular features.
There is really a large uh percentage of
our customers using it. So now we we
keep adding small functionality to it.
Uh, and we're even going to talk a
little more about it in just a moment.
>> We are. And I mean, not only a lot, it's
actually almost like um a little over
70% of all customers use analysis mode
on a monthly basis.
>> Yeah. And I don't know why the remaining
30% are not using.
>> We'll call you.
>> Yes.
>> All right. That takes us to one of the
main investments we've been doing this
year, which is to enable search by
semantic meaning on metadata, which
means finding pages, reports, queries by
similarity. The way it works is that we
take the input, we calculate a semantic
vector, and then we compare to the
semantic vectors for each of the
metadata elements, for instance, pages.
This is used in co-pilot chat. It is
used in the role explorer search and
it's used in tell me and there's
actually another one which is in the
analysis view to find related fields. Um
so that's another addition that we've
added and there is a specific session on
that as well.
Now to enable this there are actually
two feature management toggles. There is
one for advanced tellme which will
change the way the s the tell me search
looks there is there's now an advanced
tab you toggle that with one and then
for the others the chat and analysis
assist it that is the very nicely named
preview semantic similarity search and
application metadata say that quickly um
so they can be um toggled on and off
independently now what we are doing
behind the scenes is that we are keeping
the embeddings updated for these
metadata elements. So when the feature
is enabled, we generate them. If the
metadata is updated, if you change the
caption of a page, um then we will
update the embedding vector. If the
model for generating embeddings changes
and also if we change basically what is
our textual dis uh representation of an
object that it's usually based on the
caption and the about text for instance
for for reports. But of course we may
change this because we will continuously
monitor and make sure that we optimize
the search algorithm so that we get the
best hits. uh as often as possible
>> and I like you say the about text it's
both for pages queries and reports
because the better thing we feed into
the embeddings the the better is the
similarity search so if you have ISV or
PT pretended extensions make sure that
you also give good about text about
title not only for the users but also
for the AIS we kind of joke that there's
one person who reads everything and
that's the AI or open AI that reads this
right so make sure that you provide good
quality metadata and then that your
objects will light up nicely in all
these features
>> should be noted that this um maintenance
of semantic vectors happens not just for
the base app that of course happens for
all objects whether they come from app
source apps or PTE apps and the semantic
metadata search is used in advanced tell
me where you select advanced
Now
there is one thing that's different from
the existing tell me which is you need
to press enter to start the search
because word words can change meaning
dramatically when you add an extra
letter. So we actually need to know when
should we actually take the meaning of
that word or th those words. You can
write sentences as well. Um,
if you type something in the chat pane,
then we use that for finding relevant
pages. As mentioned, we use it for
adding fields in analysis views.
And it's also worth noticing that it
searches effectively in all languages.
So, you can write in a different
language than what um you currently have
in the UI. So it'll still do its best to
find the most relevant one. And it's
worth remembering that things are not
similar or not. It's always a degree of
similarity. So effectively, you always
have an ordered list of what was most
with the most similar on top. But you
can't really say that something is
either similar or not.
>> Yeah. I mean the one example is the cut
the dog cat dog food right where dogs
and cats are similar in semantic ways
they are but but dog food and dog are
likely have more similarity than dog
food and cats but it's
>> probably yes
>> but we can always second guess what the
semantic models consider um similar and
actually brings to this well I find it a
little funny that just to show that you
can write in your own language. This is
in a US version or or maybe it's the W1.
I actually can't remember but at least
it's with English as language and then I
type the Danish word for tax statement
which is mopup and it actually finds the
tax statement. That's the one on the
left. Now to the right I did it a little
shorter. So I had MS which is the VAT
tax and it finds relatives
which has probably has something to do
with mothers. Uh
>> yeah.
Um and uh yeah so in general the as Yens
mentioned there is a full session on uh
the new advanced search. Um so go watch
that here in in this launch edition as
well if you're interested in the uptake
of this
>> and also do expect that results can
change. We will adjust the algorithm for
how we treat similarity based on
measurements of what works best in
production. H
another uh area is within reporting both
document reporting and um actually all
of this is document reporting in the
platform. Uh so let me walk you through
a few things. First of all similar to a
couple of releases back we added support
for tool tips on tables that can be
inherited up. Later the same thing
happened on query objects and now we're
doing it for tool tips on record report
columns. So you could either define a
tool tip on a report uh data item field
or if you don't it will try to inherit
from the table. This means that you
could also now think about whether you
should move some of your tool tips from
pages back to the tables and they will
just inherit up in different places.
Where we use it is in the word addin
where uh this is a a new feature in the
word addin that we are shipping in this
wave as well a new data picker and uh
for the data picker where you can we
have a full session on this so go watch
that uh but the tool tips will light up
here in the UI when you hover over a
field uh you can now see the tool tip if
it is being defined. Yeah. And in
general, if you have a description of
the data, then it belongs on the table.
Now, there can be cases where you want
to elaborate on this in this given
context. Now that it is in this report,
I want to change the tool tip a little.
So that's when you would actually still
make use of the tool tip on the data
item rather than just relying on the one
in the table.
>> Correct? And that's why we like if
nothing is defined on the report object
we try to inherit from the the table but
you can override uh that in the report
object. Another thing that we are
working on is PDF and part of part of
this is both PDF UA accessible PDFs and
PDFA which is archable ones and uh we
are in the platform slowly beginning to
have support for these um in uh in the
platform. So save will default now save
in PDFUA. Eventually we'll also have um
document layouts in word in a certain
way that once they are transformed into
PDF the PDFs are accessible and can be
read in a screen reader. So this is just
the the direction things are going in
the reporting platform.
Yeah. And uh if you want to see kind of
some uptake some code uh go and and look
at the German version where we have the
souk fair format for each documents
where we both use PDFA3
as well as the embedding of of other
files of of different mime types into
the PDF.
>> I can't help but thinking of trains and
horses when I hear the word super. Yeah,
that's yeah, that is a a very German
specific joke. So, so think about that
if you don't have German or ask a German
friend.
Yes. So, we've also added some new
troubleshooting tools. Uh you can now
view SQL call information in performance
profiles. There is a session on this
particular topic about what has been
improved in the performance profile. But
effectively it's sampling and if it is
sampling during a SQL call it'll show up
here. So in general the
when it it's just like the normal AL
code that of course very short calls may
not show up.
>> Mhm.
>> And then a very small little thing the
uh app version is now included in the
copy error details.
um when you are so unlucky that you'll
find the one bug left in the product and
you want to report it.
>> Um yes. Do we have anything else because
>> um actually that
>> I had I had one thing because uh
normally
>> all the functionality we talk about
apply both to on premises and the cloud
that does not apply to the semantic
search. Correct.
>> Because we are we are maintaining the
embedding vectors etc.
um we do not have support for that in
the on-remise world. And furthermore, if
you take um and export your database,
then we're actually going to take out
the embedding vectors before um creating
the backpack because it relies on the
latest version of SQL Server, SQL Server
2025, which is available for us in Azure
SQL and for you in Azure SQL, but it's
not available yet uh for on premises.
And that's a general rule that we are
not blocking on premises in any of our
features, but it might be that a feature
is just only lightening lighting up in
the online version due to things like
this. So it's actually not that we want
to be annoying. We actually want to be
helpful that we are not breaking you and
that's because uh the the the backpack
version would kind of break you because
you don't have any way to kind of
restore that. Yeah,
>> but the rest of what you saw applies to
the on premises release as well.
>> Great. So, Yens, that is actually
everything we had for them.
>> Just a few things. Um, if you're not
following the product group on LinkedIn,
please uh not please, you should uh
ak.ms/bc
LinkedIn. It takes you to the LinkedIn
profile of uh the product group. So,
follow and get kind of weekly news of
everything that happens. Not everything
but relevant things that happened. Uh
>> there are so many things happening.
>> Yeah.
>> Um and uh the the other thing you watch
this on YouTube aka.ms/bc
YouTube is the link to the product
group's YouTube channel. Not only these
watch new but a lot of other videos
about business central co-pilot AI tips
and tricks deep dives under the hood.
under the hood. We actually have a
couple of our engineers from our team
participating this time. These are like
small snippets of things that are coming
in the next wave and um and just um
yeah, so so go and follow uh the product
group YouTube channel and if you're a
Business Central partner, the AKA link
aka.ms/bcall
is the landing page for all the AKA
links. Maybe browse it through it. we
might have added things since last time
you saw that. Uh if you're not yet on
Yammer, you are missing out compared to
your competitors. That's where a lot of
discussions, questions are happening
around the product. It's partner only.
So your competitors are there and and we
we really want you to be there as well
to be part of that community. It is
partner only. It's not for customers.
And the final link is the aka.ms/bc
office hours. This is where we from the
product group Yensis team. Uh and like
whenever we have something that is some
like new things we want to present and
also have Q&As's we do these as office
hours about 45 minutes once a month. So
program you can see that uh there. So
with this, that's actually everything we
had. Yans, should we uh say uh say
goodbye and wave?
>> Yeah, let's do that. And um see you.
>> See you.